<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-mnichols-protocols-not-the-internet-01"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="independent"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MN-UTIL-01">Protocol Architects Are Not the Creators of the Internet</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-mnichols-protocols-not-the-internet-01"/>

    <author fullname="Mark Nichols" initials="M." surname="Nichols">
          <organization>Independent</organization>
<address>
                <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
<email>mark@marknichols.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="January"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        TCP/IP standardized interoperability and end to end transport semantics. The World Wide Web standardized
        publishing and retrieval. Neither TCP/IP nor the Web specifies, provisions, or enforces the path properties
        required for utility grade Internet operation at scale.
      </t>
      <t>
        This memo defines terminology to distinguish interoperability standards from utility grade operation and
        specifies operational requirements for "infrastructure activation": provisioned transport, interconnection
        strategy, routing policy control, redundancy, locality, continuous monitoring, incident response, and
        enforceable service accountability. This memo proposes no protocol changes.
      </t>
      <t>
        Figure 1. Three layer model. Protocols enable interoperability. The Web enables publishing. Utility grade
        Internet behavior requires infrastructure activation.
      </t>
    </abstract>


    <note title="Thesis">
      <t>Protocols enable interoperability. The Web enables publishing and retrieval. Internet operation requires infrastructure activation.</t>
      <t>Protocols are necessary. They are not the Internet.</t>
    </note>

<note title="Status of This Memo">
      <t>
        This memo provides information for the Internet community. It does not specify an Internet standard of any kind.
        It is an RFC style informational memo published independently and is not an IETF document.
      </t>
    </note>

    <note title="Copyright Notice">
      <t>Copyright (c) 2026 Mark Nichols.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Public headlines and institutional profiles frequently use "created the Internet" as shorthand for protocol
        authorship. Some extend the same shorthand to the Web (HTTP, HTML, URIs). This memo separates:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t><strong>Interoperability standards</strong>, which define protocol semantics enabling heterogeneous systems and networks to exchange data.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><strong>Utility grade Internet operation</strong>, which is repeatable, measurable, and enforceable service behavior suitable for commerce and institutional dependence across borders.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <section anchor="category-statement" title="Category statement">
        <t>
          Designing protocols, or leading development of protocols or the Web software system, is not equivalent to
          creating utility grade Internet operation. A whole system creation claim requires whole system evidence.
          Protocol correctness and adoption do not imply utility grade operation.
        </t>
        <t>
          Protocol authorship is often interpreted as whole system authorship in public narratives. This memo does not
          diminish protocol invention credit. It clarifies a different claim: creation of utility grade, enforceable
          service behavior.
        </t>
        <t>
          Misattribution is now appearing in educational materials, where simplified creator narratives are presented as
          literal technical history. For example, a recent school textbook presented a single person "created the
          Internet" claim as fact.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="scope" title="Scope">
        <t>
          Protocols and the Web define semantics. The Internet is the deployed, interconnected, operated system those
          semantics run on.
        </t>
        <t>Protocols are necessary. They are not the Internet.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions and requirement language">
      <t>
        The key words MUST, MUST NOT, REQUIRED, SHALL, SHALL NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT, RECOMMENDED, MAY, and OPTIONAL in this
        memo are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 and RFC 8174.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t><strong>Interoperability:</strong> The ability of heterogeneous systems and networks to exchange data using shared protocol semantics.</t>
      <t><strong>Internet (internetwork):</strong> A network of networks in which packets can be forwarded between administrative domains.</t>
      <t><strong>Internet utility (utility grade Internet operation):</strong> A service environment in which end to end outcomes are sufficiently predictable and accountable to support commerce and institutional dependence across borders. Defining attributes include measurability, repeatability, enforceability, and operational accountability.</t>
      <t><strong>Corridor:</strong> The practical end to end path experienced by a flow, shaped by transport, interconnection, routing policy, and queue treatment.</t>
      <t><strong>Infrastructure activation:</strong> The work required to turn interoperable networking into a dependable utility, including provisioned transport, interconnection strategy, routing policy control, redundancy, locality, and continuous operations.</t>
      <t><strong>Activation gap:</strong> The difference between: (a) standards compliant endpoint behavior, and (b) corridor properties required for predictable long lived sessions and secure transactions across borders.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="problem" title="Problem statement: interoperability without utility">
      <t>
        In an interoperable internetwork, reachability may exist while utility grade behavior does not. The activation gap
        exists when endpoints remain standards compliant but corridor properties fall outside the envelope required by
        applications and transactions.
      </t>

      <section anchor="failure-modes" title="Common failure modes">
        <t>The following observable conditions can occur while protocols remain correct:</t>
        <ul>
          <li><t>high RTT variance and multi second spikes</t></li>
          <li><t>loss and jitter that collapse long lived sessions</t></li>
          <li><t>congested interconnects and chokepoints</t></li>
          <li><t>policy driven queue treatment and class of service degradation</t></li>
          <li><t>middlebox or application time budgets expiring before recovery converges</t></li>
          <li><t>unstable routing policy interactions under load or failure</t></li>
        </ul>
        <t>These failures are utility failures, not protocol definition failures.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tcpip" title="What TCP/IP and routing do, and do not do">
      <section anchor="tcp" title="TCP transport semantics">
        <t>
          TCP provides end to end transport semantics between endpoints, including reliable delivery, ordering, flow
          control, congestion response, and session recovery state.
        </t>
        <t>TCP does not and cannot guarantee corridor viability across independent networks. Specifically, TCP:</t>
        <ul>
          <li><t>does not select paths and does not control interdomain routing policy</t></li>
          <li><t>does not provision capacity or ensure headroom</t></li>
          <li><t>does not require redundancy or diverse corridors to exist</t></li>
          <li><t>does not enforce priority, scheduling, or QoS across domains</t></li>
          <li><t>cannot prevent application or middlebox timeouts</t></li>
          <li><t>does not provide network operations alarms by itself</t></li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ip-bgp" title="IP and interdomain routing">
        <t>IP provides addressing and forwarding semantics and a best effort abstraction for internetworking.</t>
        <t>
          IP and interdomain routing protocols can exchange reachability and can support failover only when alternate
          topology exists and policy permits its use. Reachability is not equivalent to utility. Interconnect capacity
          and routing policy frequently dominate user outcomes.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="web" title="What the Web does, and does not do">
      <t>
        The Web defines a publishing and retrieval system: naming (URIs), retrieval (HTTP request and response), and
        documents with links (HTML) implemented in clients and servers.
      </t>
      <t>The Web does not create corridor viability or utility grade delivery. It:</t>
      <ul>
        <li><t>does not create transport capacity or corridor headroom</t></li>
        <li><t>does not control interconnection capacity, routing policy, or queue treatment</t></li>
        <li><t>does not ensure that secure sessions complete at global distance</t></li>
        <li><t>does not provide operational accountability for performance</t></li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The Web can make "content exists" true. It cannot make "content arrives predictably at distance" true without an
        engineered corridor underneath.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="requirements" title="Requirements for utility grade Internet operation">
      <t>
        A deployment that claims utility grade Internet operation across borders MUST satisfy the requirements in this
        section for the scope of its claimed service.
      </t>

      <section anchor="transport-provisioning" title="Transport provisioning">
        <t>
          The operator MUST provision transport with sufficient headroom to keep RTT variance, loss, and jitter within
          bounds required by intended sessions and transactions.
        </t>
        <t>The operator SHOULD provision diverse corridors across meaningful failure domains (facility, carrier, geography).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="interconnection" title="Interconnection capacity and strategy">
        <t>
          The operator MUST ensure POP level interconnection capacity consistent with intended service outcomes,
          including port capacity, cross connects, exchange strategy, and congestion avoidance at handoffs.
        </t>
        <t>The operator MUST treat persistent interconnect congestion as a service failure requiring remediation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="routing-policy" title="Routing policy control">
        <t>
          The operator MUST implement routing policy control using operator controlled equipment and AS level intent at
          backbone facing handoffs.
        </t>
        <t>The operator MUST validate failover behavior under realistic failure conditions and policy constraints.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="redundancy" title="Redundancy and disaster recovery">
        <t>
          The operator MUST implement redundancy across meaningful failure domains and MUST demonstrate that redundancy
          is usable under policy and operational constraints.
        </t>
        <t>The operator SHOULD conduct regular failover and restoration drills.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="locality" title="Locality">
        <t>
          The operator SHOULD implement locality via distributed hosting, caching, replication, or placement to reduce
          dependency on long haul corridors for common retrieval paths and transaction flows.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="continuous-ops" title="Continuous operations">
        <t>
          The operator MUST implement continuous operations sufficient to detect, isolate, and remediate corridor
          failures and performance collapse, including monitoring, alerting, escalation, incident response, and change
          control.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="accountability" title="Accountability and enforceability">
        <t>
          The operator MUST define measurable obligations appropriate to the claimed service, including targets,
          reporting, accountability, and enforceable commitments such as SLAs and remedies.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="attribution" title="Attribution clarification">
      <t>
        It is technically accurate to credit protocol architects and standards bodies for interoperability. It is not
        technically accurate to credit interoperability standards alone for the emergence of a commercial utility.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Internet utility is an operational outcome produced by infrastructure activation and operations discipline at
        scale. Protocols are necessary for interoperability. They are not sufficient for utility grade behavior.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security considerations">
      <t>
        This memo proposes no protocol changes. Predictable completion of secure sessions depends on corridor viability
        and on operational practices including monitoring, incident response, and accountable interconnection. Corridor
        instability and policy driven impairment SHOULD be treated as availability and security risks, not merely
        performance issues.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="references" title="References">
      <section anchor="normative" title="Normative References">
        <t>RFC 2119. Key words for use in RFCs to indicate requirement levels.</t>
        <t>RFC 8174. Ambiguity of uppercase vs lowercase in RFC 2119 key words.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="informative" title="Informative References">
        <t>RFC 1122. Requirements for Internet Hosts. Communication Layers.</t>
        <t>RFC 9293. Transmission Control Protocol (TCP).</t>
        <t>RFC 4271. Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back/>

</rfc>
